Finding Aid for Samuel Miller Brownell and Esther Delzell Brownell papers, 1900-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Samuel Miller Brownell and Esther Delzell Brownell papers 1900-2003
Brownell, Samuel Miller, 1900-
2010176 Aa 2; Ac
Samuel Miller Brownell was an educator and school administrator who served as U.S. Commissioner of Education from 1953-1956 and as Superintendent of Detroit Public Schools from 1956 to 1966. He was married to Esther Delzell Brownell, who taught high school history before their 1927 marriage. This collection documents the Brownells’ family life, and to a lesser extent, Samuel M. Brownell’s career. Materials include a large collection of correspondence between Samuel and Esther Brownell, personal papers reflecting the family’s social and cultural activities and daily life, and a series of scrapbooks, dating from 1900 to 1988, containing photographs, clippings, newsletters, correspondence, and ephemera. The older scrapbooks provide information about the early lives of both of the Brownells, and later scrapbooks document the family’s vacations and Samuel Brownell’s career as an educator, administrator, and political appointee.
20 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by the children of Samuel Miller Brownell and Esther Delzell Brownell: Ruth Brownell Green (donor no. 10346 ), Jane Brownell Cheek (donor no. 10393 ), Richard Miller Brownell, and Dorothy Brownell Templeton.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Samuel Miller Brownell was born in 1900 in Peru, Nebraska. He received his B.A. from the University of Nebraska in 1921, his M.A. from Yale University in 1924, and his Ph.D. from Yale in 1926. Brownell was an educator, administrator, and consultant in the field of urban educational administration. His first professional post was at the New York State College of Teachers. From 1927 to 1938, he was Superintendent of Schools in Grosse Pointe, Michigan. In 1938, he joined the faculty of Yale as a professor of educational administration. From 1947 to 1953, he was President of New Haven State Teacher's College, concurrent with his work at Yale. He resigned both positions when he was appointed U.S. Commissioner of Education by President Eisenhower in 1953. His brother, Herbert Brownell, also worked for the Eisenhower administration, serving as U.S. Attorney General from 1953 to 1957. In 1956, Samuel Brownell left Washington to become Superintendent of Detroit Public Schools. He returned to New Haven in 1966, where he held a joint position at Yale and the University of Connecticut. He retired in 1973. In the mid 1970s, he served as a consultant for Development & Resources Corporation, which conducted the Iran Public Sector Management Program, a diagnostic review of Iran’s public sector. Brownell died in 1990.
Esther Delzell Brownell was born in 1902 in Syracuse, Nebraska. Her family moved to Peru, Nebraska in 1905. She attended Peru State Normal School for her primary and secondary education, graduating with a B.A. in English and Education in 1923. After graduation, she taught history at the high school level until her marriage to Samuel Brownell in 1927. The Brownells had four children: Richard, born in 1930, Dorothy, in 1932, Jane, in 1937, and Ruth, in 1944. Esther Brownell was active in a number of social and philanthropic organizations. She was a life-long member of P.E.O., a philanthropic educational organization; and while living in Detroit, she served on the Women’s Committee of the United Community Services and the Board of Directors of the YWCA; and she was a sponsor for students visiting the U.S. through the American Field Service’s international scholarship program. Esther Brownell died a year after her husband, in 1991.
The Samuel Miller Brownell and Esther Delzell Brownell collection documents the family life of two individuals from their courtship through their old age. To a lesser extent, the career of Samuel Brownell as educator is also documented. The papers are arranged roughly chronologically into three series, beginning with the lives of each of the Brownells before their marriage, and then following them as they moved from Nebraska to Michigan, to Connecticut, to Washington, D.C., to Michigan again, and finally to back to Connecticut.
Subjects:
Brownell, Esther Delzell, 1902-1991.; Brownell, Samuel Miller, 1900-1990; Education--Iran.; Education--Michigan--Detroit.; Education--United States--History--20th century.; School superintendents--Michigan--Detroit.; School superintendents--Michigan--Grosse Pointe.; United States. Office of Education.
Contributors:
Brownell, Esther Delzell, 1902-1991.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Samuel Miller Brownell Papers 1909-1989
  The Samuel Miller Brownell Papers date from 1909 to 1989, and document some of his professional activities and his personal life prior to his marriage. This series includes a significant number of letters Brownell received from Esther Delzell during their courtship. The letters, which are very frequent, discuss Delzell’s daily activities, her social life, her family, and her work as a teacher. The letters offer a glimpse of the life of a young working woman in the 1920s. Other items in this series are a postcard from Brownell to his grandmother, Mrs. Samuel Miller, a dramatization of Silas Marner written by Brownell, a letter noting his discharge from the Student’s Army Training Corps in 1918, Brownell’s curriculum vitae, and several photographs. The series also includes essays by Brownell on the subject of school administration, papers documenting his work as a consultant on the Iran Public Sector Management Program, and a catalog of the books Brownell donated to Southern Connecticut State University.
  - Awards and certificates 1927-1989 (Box 1)
  - Biographical undated (Box 1)
    (includes curriculum vitae and photographs)
  - Correspondence from Esther Delzell to Samuel Brownell 1925-1927, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence from Samuel Brownell to Mrs. Samuel Miller 1909 (Box 1)
  - Silas Marner dramatization 1914 (Box 1)
  - Student's Army Training Corps discharge 1918 (Box 1)
  - Concerns of a School Administrator I and II undated, 3 folders (Box 17)
    (essays by SMB)
  - Catalog of SMB Professional Library Collection at Southern Connecticut State University 1984 (Box 17)
  - Iran Public Sector Management Program
    - Phase I and Phase II reports 1975 (Box 20)
    - Reports and team assignments (Box 20)
    - Activity reports (Box 20)
    - Correspondence and memos, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - SMB Report on Ministry of Education 1976 (Box 20)
    - Ministry of Education review papers (Box 20)
    - SMB notes (Box 20)
      (includes notes on education and the people and culture of Iran)
    - Receipts and expenses (Box 20)
    - SMB travel journal and letters to family (Box 20)
    - Printed material (Box 20)
    - Clippings (Box 20)
- Esther Delzell Papers 1910-1974
  The bulk of the Esther Delzell Papers is made up of letters from Samuel Brownell. His letters, written while he was at Yale, and later at the New York State College for Teachers at Albany, describe the completion of his Ph.D. and the beginnings of his professional career. The letters, written nearly every day, are loving and often funny. They provide a good sense of his day to day experiences and demonstrate his focus on his new career. Other materials in this series include Delzell’s diary, kept between 1915 and 1917, a few items relating to her education and teaching post, and letters and cards from friends, 1917-1927.
  - Correspondence
    - From Samuel Brownell to Esther Delzell 1923-1927, undated, 13 folders (Box 1)
      (includes CD of transcriptions of 1923-1925 letters)
    - From friends, arranged alphabetically 1917-1927, 30 folders (Box 2)
    - From Esther Delzell to family 1917-1926 (Box 2)
  - Personal: Education, Teaching, etc.
    - Campfire Girls 1916-1919 (Box 2)
    - Clubs, theatre, and social events 1914-1927 (Box 2)
    - Cooking demonstration and recipes, undated circa 1920 (Box 2)
    - Diary 1915-1917 (Box 2)
    - Peru State Normal School diploma, papers, and ephemera 1920-1923 (Box 2)
    - Peru State Normal School newsletters 1910-1922 (Box 2)
    - School essays, undated circa 1918 (Box 2)
    - Teaching 1923-1926 (Box 2)
    - Travel 1922-1926 (Box 2)
    - Wedding announcements and lists 1927 (Box 2)
    - Wilson estate 1934-1974, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (estates of Enoch H. Wilson and Andrew J. Wilson)
    - Miscellaneous papers and ephemera 1910-1927, undated (Box 2)
- Brownell Family Papers 1900-2003
  The Brownell Family Papers is the largest series in the collection, and has been divided into eight subseries: Correspondence; five separate subseries for each of the family's places of residence, Grosse Pointe (1927-1937), New Haven (1937-1954), Washington, D.C. (1954-1956), Detroit (1956-1966), and New Haven (1966-1991); a subseries of scrapbooks and photographs albums; and a subseries of Calendars and School Records.
  - Correspondence 1927-1990, undated
    Correspondence includes letters exchanged by Samuel and Esther Brownell, letters written by both Brownells to family members, and letters and cards received from friends. Like the letters from their courtship period, the letters the Brownells exchanged while they were separated by work or travel, provide details of their family activities, and their work and social involvements.
    - From Samuel Brownell to Esther Brownell 1927-1934, undated, 6 folders
      - To William Delzell 1929, undated (Box 3)
      - To Brownell family 1928-1940 (Box 3)
      - To May Miller Brownell 1953-1956 (Box 3)
      - To brothers and sisters 1966-1975, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - From Esther Brownell to Samuel Brownell 1927-1953, undated, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - From Esther Brownell to William Delzell 1935-1940, undated (Box 4)
    - Round robin letters 1953-1972, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - From friends, arranged alphabetically, A-H 1927-1989, 48 folders (Box 4)
    - From friends, arranged alphabetically, I-Z 1927-1989, 50 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, unsorted 1985-1990 (Box 5)
    - Condolence letters to Esther Brownell and family 1990, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Grosse Pointe 1927-1937
    The Grosse Pointe files include a variety of material, such as clippings, invitations and programs for social and cultural events, calendars and address books, household lists, drawings by the Brownell children, and ephemera.
    - Banking 1930-1933 (Box 5)
    - Calendars 1930-1934 (Box 5)
    - Church bulletins and other materials 1929-1931 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, miscellaneous 1927-1928, undated (Box 5)
    - Clubs, theatre, and social events 1929-1935 (Box 5)
    - Grosse Pointe School District materials 1928-1938 (Box 5)
    - Household lists and receipts 1930-1937 (Box 5)
    - Peru State Normal Alumni Association certificate 1930 (Box 5)
    - Photographs of friends, circa 1910s-1940 (Box 5)
    - St. Helen, Michigan materials 1935, undated (Box 5)
    - Travel, New Orleans and Florida 1928-1937 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous papers and ephemera 1927-1937, undated (Box 5)
  - New Haven 1937-1954
    The New Haven files include a variety of material, such as clippings, invitations and programs for social and cultural events, calendars and address books, household lists, drawings by the Brownell children, and ephemera.
    - Calendars 1939-1953 (Box 6)
    - Calling card plates and blank stationery undated (Box 6)
    - Children's drawings and school papers 1948-1951, undated (Box 6)
    - Church bulletins and related materials 1949-1953 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, miscellaneous 1940-1953 (Box 6)
    - Clubs, theatre, and social events 1940-1948 (Box 6)
    - Grosse Pointe 1938-1953 (Box 6)
    - Household lists and receipts 1944-1951 (Box 6)
    - Peru, Nebraska 1947-1948, undated (Box 6)
    - New Haven State Teachers College 1948-1950 (Box 6)
    - Southern Connecticut State University history 1988 (Box 6)
    - Travel, Hawaii 1946 (Box 6)
    - World War II circulars and ephemera 1940-1947 (Box 6)
    - Yale correspondence, invitations, and related materials 1938-1951 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers and ephemera 1939-1956, undated (Box 6)
  - Washington, D.C. 1952-1956
    These files include a variety of material, such as clippings, invitations and programs for social and cultural events, calendars and address books, household lists, and ephemera.
    - Church bulletins and other materials 1954-1956 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, Samuel and Esther Brownell 1953-1956 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, Herbert and Doris Brownell 1952-1956 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, Secretary of H.E.W. Oveta Culp Hobby 1954-1955 (Box 6)
    - Clippings, Dwight and Mamie Eisenhower 1954-1956 (Box 6)
    - Clubs and social events 1954-1956, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Itineraries, Samuel Brownell 1954-1956 (Box 7)
    - Republican Women's Organizations 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - Speeches, Esther Brownell 1956 (Box 7)
    - Speeches and Department of Education Business, Samuel Brownell 1954-1955 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous papers and ephemera 1954-1956, undated (Box 7)
  - Detroit 1956-1966
    - Addresses and address book 1950s-1960s (Box 7)
    - American Field Service papers, correspondence, and photographs, 1963-1968, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Church bulletins and other materials 1958 (Box 7)
    - Clippings, Detroit Free Press Sunday Supplement on Esther Brownell 1962 (Box 7)
    - Clippings, Detroit Free Press "Report Card" column by Samuel Brownell 1962, undated (Box 7)
    - Clippings, Detroit Public Schools 1959-1964 (Box 7)
    - Clippings, miscellaneous 1958-1963 (Box 7)
    - Clubs, theatre, social, and civic events 1956-1966, 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Detroit Public Schools, newsletters, brochures, and correspondence 1956-1966 (Box 8)
    - Grosse Pointe 1958-1965 (Box 8)
    - Peru, Nebraska, newsletters, clippings, and miscellaneous materials 1957-1965 (Box 8)
    - Peru State Normal School alumni list and essay by Ruth Brownell 1957, 1965 (Box 8)
    - Travel, Hawaii and Seattle 1962-1964 (Box 8)
    - Travel, England, Europe, and Venezuela, and travel documents 1958-1964 (Box 8)
    - United Community Services 1957-1963 (Box 8)
    - Warwick Street House (16525 Warwick St., Detroit) (Box 8)
    - YWCA 1957-1961 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous papers and ephemera 1957-1961, undated (Box 8)
  - New Haven 1966-1991
    - Anniversaries, invitation for 50th, and video of 60th 1977, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Articles by Samuel Brownell 1971, circa 1989 (Box 8)
    - Biographical information, Samuel and Esther Brownell 1919, circa 1955, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Birthdays, Samuel Brownell 1970, 1975 (Box 8)
    - Brownell family recollections, audiocassette and booklet 1984, 2003 (Box 8)
    - Church bulletins and other materials 1967-1990 (Box 8)
    - Clippings, Samuel Brownell 1954-1974 (Box 8)
    - Clippings, miscellaneous 1967-1979 (Box 8)
    - Clubs, theatre, and social events 1967-1989 (Box 9)
    - Education societies, organizations, and programs 1969-1988 (Box 9)
    - Memorial video, Esther Brownell 1991 (Box 9)
    - Passports (Box 9)
    - Peru, Nebraska, sketches of town circa 1985 (Box 9)
    - Peru State College 1968-1989 (Box 9)
    - Research files, Esther Brownell 1971-1975, undated (Box 9)
    - Speeches, Esther Brownell, undated circa 1960s-1970s (Box 9)
    - Travel, Alaska, Canada, Hawaii 1968-1970 (Box 9)
    - Travel, Iran and Jordan 1976 (Box 9)
    - Tributes, Samuel Brownell 1967-1986 (Box 9)
    - Wills, obituaries, and estate information 1990-1993 (Box 9)
    - Yale invitations, programs, and clippings 1968-1989 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous papers and ephemera 1968-1989, undated, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks and Photo Albums, 1900-1998
    The final subseries, Scrapbooks and Photo Albums, contains disbound scrapbook pages from 1900 to 1988. The early scrapbooks, from 1900 to 1927, include ephemera from the school and social lives of both Esther Delzell and Samuel Brownell. From 1927 to 1988, the main emphasis of the scrapbooks becomes Samuel Brownell's career as an educator and administrator, although they also contain photographs and ephemera relating the Brownell family and their friends. The items in the scrapbooks that document Brownell's career include letters received by and copies of letters sent by Brownell; newsletters, brochures, and programs; photographs of Brownell attending conferences, graduation ceremonies, and other events; newspaper clippings about Brownell; clippings of the "Report Card," a Detroit Free Press column written by Brownell in 1961-1962; clippings about Herbert Brownell's political career; and various invitations and ephemera.
    The Scrapbooks and Photo Albums subseries also includes a disbound photo album entitled "The Schools that Sam Built," showing images of elementary, middle, and high school buildings in the Detroit Public School system; a packet of reports and agendas from a meeting of the Inter-American Ministers of Education, held in Lima, Peru in 1956; a scrapbook from a trip taken by the wives of Eisenhower administration Cabinet members in 1956 (this trip included the Brownells' sister-in-law, Doris Brownell); and photos from the dedication of a portrait of Brownell at Southern Connecticut State College in 1974.
    The travel scrapbooks are well annotated, and include photos, postcards, maps, and ephemera documenting the family’s travels around North American and abroad. This subseries also includes disbound photo albums and commemorative volumes related to Brownell’s roles as school superintendent, Commissioner of Education, and educational consultant.
    - 1900-1917, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - 1916-1933 Esther Delzell and Samuel and Esther Brownell scrapbook pages (Folder 1)
      (located at B-608-T)
    - 1917-1926, 8 folders (Box 10)
    - 1927-1935, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - 1926-1955, 15 folders (Box 11)
    - Jan-June 1956, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Esther Brownell, National Federation of Republican Women April 1956 (Box 12)
    - Samuel Brownell, Inter-American Ministers of Education meeting May 1956 (Box 12)
    - 1956-1961, 11 folders (Box 12)
    - 1962-1965, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - "The Schools that Sam Built" photographs 1966, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - 1966-1969, 7 folders (Box 13)
    - 1970-1974, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Samuel Brownell portrait dedication at Southern Connecticut State College 1974 (Box 14)
    - 1975-1988, 14 folders (Box 14)
    - Travel scrapbooks
      - Honolulu 1946 (Box 15)
      - Europe 1958, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Hawaii 1964-1968, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Norway 1966 (Box 15)
      - Sweden and Denmark 1966, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Alaska 1968, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Olympic Peninsula and Canadian Rockies 1969, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Quebec/Gaspe 1970 (Box 16)
      - Grand Midwest Tour 1974 (Box 16)
      - Iran 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 16)
        (see also Iran Public Sector Management Program)
      - Mexico 1978 (Box 16)
    - 50th wedding anniversary 1977, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Samuel Brownell career scrapbooks
      - School Administration Morgue, Grosse Pointe Schools 1917-1938 (Box 16)
        (samples of administrative paperwork kept by SMB)
      - President's Committee on Physical Fitness 1946 (Box 16)
      - SMB U.S. Commissioner of Education photographs 1953-1956 (Box 16)
      - UNESCO Conference, Montevideo, Uruguay 1954, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Letters on Leaving Office of Education 1956 (Box 17)
      - Visit to 28th Joint Civilian Orientation Conference, Fort Bening, GA 1959 (Box 17)
      - Detroit Schools dedication programs 1961-1966 (Box 17)
      - Venezuela (workshop on Supervision) 1964 (Box 17)
      - Superintendent's 100th and Final Meeting of Principals and Supervisors (Detroit Schools) 1966 (Box 17)
        (roster of attendees and photographs)
      - Detroit Schools, Region Seven Music Festival 1966 (Box 17)
        (music dedicated to SMB)
      - U.S. Coast Guard Advisory Board photographs undated (Box 17)
  - Calendars and School Records
    The final subseries, Calendars and School Records, contains personal calendars of Samuel Brownell for most years between 1916 and 1989, calendars of Esther Delzell for scattered years, and work calendars of Samuel Brownell from 1937-1943, 1958-1959, and 1962-1974. The subseries also includes record books for classes Samuel Brownell taught at the University of Nebraska between 1921 and 1927, and several miscellaneous volumes related to Brownell’s teaching posts in Peru, Nebraska and at Yale University.
    - SMB and EDB desk and pocket calendars 1924-1989 (Box 18)
    - SMB school desk calendars 1937-1943, 1958-1959, 1962-1974 (Box 19)
    - SMB budget and account book 1924-1925 (Box 19)
    - Expenses 1969 (Box 19)
    - Masons, Monitor and Ceremonies, Nebraska (Box 19)
    - Class notes and poems 1942 (Box 19)
      (possibly notes for courses taught at Yale)
    - Record of discipline cases, Peru High School 1921-1923 (Box 19)
    - SMB student pocket calendars 1916-1921, 5 volumes (Box 19)
    - Class record books 1921-1927, 5 volumes (Box 19)
Related Material
Papers of Samuel Miller Brownell are also held at Yale University Library Manuscripts and Archives. The Samuel Miller Brownell papers, 1923-1986, bulk 1966-1975 (MS 1491), primarily document Brownell's tenure at Yale University and the University of Connecticut.